Today's דף daf *daf* is כ"ד *Kaf Daled*, but we kick up
at the bottom of כ"א עמוד amud, ב' *Kaf Alef Amud Bet*
or maybe middle of כ"א עמוד amud, ב' *Kaf Alef Amud Bet*.
We're talking about the way they would salt the meat or the
everything they would burn in the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash *Beit HaMikdash*.
And we are אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *Amar lei Ravina le-Rav
Ashi*. It is about exactly down the middle of the narrow lines.
There's a little ויקרא ו' *Vayikra vav* in square brackets in the
right hand column between the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and the תוספות Tosafot,
*Tosafot*. And the line starts with the word להו *lehu*. So we
pick up there. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *Amar lei Ravina le-Rav
Ashi*, פשיטא *Pshita*, Ravina asked Rav
Ashi.
So we had already established that there was a difference. We give
the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* salt to use for their קרבן korban *korban*
meat that they eat. That goes with the thing that we give
them salt for when they offer their קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* and put
it on the מזבח mizbeiach, *Mizbeach*, the same way we would give
to anybody who brought a קרבן korban *korban*. But we also give
them salt to use, the same salt that we have there, to
use on eating their קרבן korban *korban* meat but not on eating
their non-קרבן korban *korban* meat that they eat, you know, together with
their קרבן korban. *korban* meat. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to continue with this. So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *Amar lei
Ravina le-Rav Ashi*, so Ravina said to Rav Ashi, הכי נמי מסתברא
*hachi nami mistavra*, that also makes sense. דאי סלקא דעתך מהי קרבנן
למלוח *de-ee salka daitach mai korbanan linloach*, because if you had said
it the other way that we give them meat for putting the
salt on their קרבן korban. *korban* that they're going to
burn, טעמא דאתני בית דין Beit Din *Ta'ama de-atni Beit Din*. So
the reason, so the we said that בית דין Beit Din, *Beit
Din* stipulated to give them this salt, made a special condition. הא
לא lo, אתני בית דין Beit Din לא *Ha lo atni Beit
Din lo*, if בית דין Beit Din *Beit Din* had not stipulated,
no, we would not give them salt even to put their own
קרבן korban *korban* on the מזבח mizbeach. *Mizbeach*. So that doesn't make
any sense. השתא לישראל יהבינא לכהנים לא יהבינא *Hashta l'Yisrael yahvina le-Kohanim
lo yahvina*? What sense would it make that you need a special
stipulation to give the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* salt to put on their
meat that they're going to burn on the מזבח Mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*? I
mean we give it to a normal ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael*, why would
we not give it to a כהן Kohen *Kohen*? Why would you
need a special stipulation? דתניא Detanya, *De-tanya*, and how do we know
we give a normal person who brings a קרבן korban, *korban* the
salt? The בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash? *Beit HaMikdash* provides the salt for
the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. דתניא *De-tanya*, we taught in the ברייתא beraita
*Baraita*. יכול האומר הרי עלי מנחה mincha, יביא מלח מתוך ביתו כדרך
שמביא לבונה levona. מתוך ביתו *Yakhol ha-omer harei alai mincha yavi melach
mi-toch beito kederech she-mevi levona mi-toch beito*. Maybe if a person says
I'm going to bring a מנחה mincha, *mincha*, maybe he has to
provide the salt the same way he provides the לבונה levona. *levona*.
And the comparison is apt because, you know, by a מנחה mincha
*mincha*, he only obligated himself with a מנחה mincha *mincha* and the
תורה Torah *Torah* demands that a לבונה levona *levona* accompany it. But
he never should have said I'm going to bring a מנחה mincha
*mincha* with the frankincense. So if he has to bring the לבונה
levona *levona* that accompanies it because the תורה Torah *Torah* is demanding
it, maybe he should also have to bring the salt. ודינהו *Ve-dinhu*,
and it makes sense. נאמר הבא מנחה mincha והבא מלח *Ne'emar havei
mincha ve-havei melach*, it says bring מנחה mincha *mincha* and it says
bring salt, ונאמר הבא מנחה mincha והבא לבונה levona *ve-ne'emar havei mincha
ve-havei levona*. The תורה Torah *Torah* says when you bring a מנחה
mincha *mincha* you have to put salt on it.
Are you getting it now, Jed?
Testing. All right. What is frankincense? לבונה levona, *Levona*.
I have no idea.
Okay, so where are we? All right, so the
תורה Torah *Torah* says bring מנחה mincha *mincha*, it says bring with
it salt, and it says bring מנחה mincha *mincha* and it says
bring with it לבונה levonah *levona*. So I would think so, let's
continue.
So the line starts with the word ודינהו *Ve-dinhu*, about two-thirds of
the way down. ודינהו *Ve-dinhu*, נאמר הבא מנחה mincha. והבא מלח *ne'emar
havei mincha ve-havei melach*, that is really distracting me. ונאמר הבא מנחה
mincha והבא לבונה levonah *Ve-ne'emar havei mincha ve-havei levona*. מה לבונה מתוך
ביתו אף מלח מתוך ביתו *Ma levona mi-toch beito af melach mi-toch
beito*. The same way you have to provide the frankincense from your
house, you have to provide, maybe I would think you provide the
salt from your house. או כלך לדרך זו *O kelach l'derech zu*,
or go this way. נאמר הבא מנחה mincha והבא מלח *Ne'emar havei
mincha ve-havei melach*,
ונאמר הבא מנחה mincha והבא עצים *ve-ne'emar havei mincha ve-havei etzin*. Maybe
I should say look, it says bring a מנחה mincha *mincha*, put
salt on it, and it says bring a מנחה mincha *mincha*, thank
you, and burn it on wood. מה עצים משל ציבור tzibur, *Ma
etzin mishel tzibur*, the same way we take it for granted, and
we're going to disprove that in a minute, that the wood is
provided by the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*, אף מלח משל
ציבור tzibur. *af melach mishel tzibur*. So the salt maybe is provided
by the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. So basically what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is like this. Who provides the salt?
And if you look at a מנחה mincha *mincha*, we're taking it
for granted two things: that when you bring a מנחה mincha. *mincha*,
you bring the לבונה *levona*. Michael wants to know how do you
know you bring the לבונה *levona*. So one of the reasons is
because when the תורה Torah *Torah* says that you, it only mentions
the כהן Kohen *Kohen* after you've already brought לבונה *levona*, right? And
normally we say that tells you you're allowed to do certain things
before the קמיצה *kemitza*. Right? But we also learn we are inferring
from it in terms of who's providing the קרבן korban, *korban*. So
when it speaks about the מנחה mincha *mincha*, it says...
Where is it? ואם מנחה mincha. על המחבת קרבנו, I'm sorry, ונפש
כי תקריב קרבן מנחה להשם סולת יהיה קרבנו ויצק עליה שמן ונתן
עליה לבונה, ve-nefesh ki takriv korban mincha la-Hashem, solet yihye korbano, ve-yatzak
aleha shemen, ve-natan aleha levona, so till you והביאה אל בני אהרן
הכהן. ve-hevia el benei Aharon ha-Kohen. So we take it for granted
that you're bringing the מנחה, you bring the לבונה. We're also taking
for granted the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash provides the wood for the
מזבח, mizbeach? which sort of makes sense. So now there's this case
of the salt. Who is providing the salt? You, the person bringing
the מנחה, or the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash Logically, if you'd ask
me, I would say, and this is the way we rule, but
it's provided by the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash If the salt goes
on every single קרבן korban. or every קרבן korban. that satisfies certain
parameters, it's not something specific to your קרבן korban and it's part
of the general operating expense of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash like
the wood. But the גמרא Gemara is saying how do I know
that? Okay, it's barely audible, again, it's barely audible. אוי. oy. All
right,
still something's with this new, sorry, the other one wasn't working. Can
you go to my office and my box and get the other
thing? Yeah.
I'm sorry, bear with me a minute. Moving really up.
All right, we're going to try another microphone in a minute. All
right,
anyway, so who is providing the salt? Where were we? והרי נאמר
הביא מנחה והביא מלח ונאמר הביא מנחה והביא לבונה. ve-harei ne-emar havi
mincha ve-havi melach ve-ne-emar havi mincha ve-havi levona. So the גמרא Gemara
says נימא למי דומה, nima le-mi domeh, where are we? אף אתה,
נימא למי דומה. af ata, nima le-mi domeh. Let's see which one
it's more comparable to. All right, always some technological thing getting in
our way.
What are you doing there, Matt? A few questions?
Yeah. Isn't there also an implied logic here that if you're expecting
people to bring not only the קרבן korban but the salt, you
could just mess up the whole system because somebody forgot, people forgot
salt, and I mean if it's there it's there. They
don't forget the קרבן. korban. Right, right, that's a good point too.
That's a good point too. But
all right, all right, okay. Now hopefully everything will be good.
All right, back to where we were. What do you say?
Yeah, no, I hear that. That makes a lot of sense. All
right, so now the גמרא's Gemara trying to figure out who brings
the salt, and let's take a look. It says, all right, נימא
למי דומה, nima le-mi domeh, line starting with דומה, domeh, about six
lines before it got wide. דנין דבר הנוהג בכל הזבחים מדבר הנוהג
בכל הזבחים. danin davar ha-noheg be-khol ha-zevachim mi-davar ha-noheg be-khol ha-zevachim. Right,
so you take something that applies by all קרבנות korbanot, like wood,
like wood,
and you compare it to something, well, okay, or salt, and you
apply it to something that applies to all קרבנות korbanot like wood.
ואל יוכיחו לבונה שאינה נוהגת בכל הזבחים. ve-al yokhichu levona she-eina noheget
be-khol ha-zevachim. And don't bring the proof from לבונה. And it's
not only like an incidental comparison, I think it is, like I
was saying, you know, the wood and the salt are part of
the operating, you know, the operations of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash.
and their normal operating expenses as opposed to the לבונה which is
something that comes with the מנחה and it's part of the קרבן.
korban So that's what we would normally say. Or maybe not. או
כלך לדרך זו דנין דבר הבא עמו בכלי אחד מדבר הבא עמו
בכלי אחד. o kelakh le-derekh zu, danin davar ha-ba imo bi-khli echad
mi-davar ha-ba imo bi-khli echad. How about the fact that the לבונה
you put in with the vessel of the מנחה before you, at
least before you take the קומץ. kometz. And the salt you put
into the vessel that holds the קומץ. kometz. So at least they
become unified. So if you look at it that way, although salt
is this by all of the קרבנות, korbanot? nevertheless it is more
like part of the קרבן korban. than the wood. So maybe anything
that is conceived of as part of the קרבן, korban maybe that
is something that you, actually the owner, would have to provide. Okay.
תלמוד לומר ואל יוכיחו עצים שאינם באים בכלי אחד. talmud lomar ve-al
yokhichu etzim she-einam ba-im bi-khli echad. The wood is not part of
the קרבן, korban. it's not in the same vessel, it's on the
fire. תלמוד לומר ברית מלח עולם היא, talmud lomar berit melach olam
hi, ולהלן הוא אומר מאת בני ישראל ברית עולם. ve-lahalan hu omer
me-et benei Yisrael berit olam.
So by the ברית berit to the כהנים Kohanim it calls it
a ברית מלח עולם, berit melach olam, and it says מאת בני
ישראל ברית עולם me-et benei Yisrael berit olam by, what was that
by? Hold on.
By the לחם הפנים. lechem ha-panim. מה להלן משל ציבור, ma lahalan
mi-shel tzibur, so the same way the לחם הפנים lechem ha-panim comes
from the ציבור, tzibur, אף כאן משל ציבור, af kan mi-shel tzibur,
here too from the ציבור. tzibur. Okay, we've had a lot of
adjusting ourselves this morning, hopefully we're all settled down. Okay, anyway, so
where are we? We basically said a very straightforward ברייתא Baraita, which
is the salt is provided by the ציבור, tzibur not by the
person who brings it, because it's more similar. to the wood in
the fact that it you do it by all the קרבנות Korbanot
so the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, provides it even though maybe I
would have said it's like the מנחה because you put it on
the מנחה so the same way you bring the מנחה and the
לבונה you bring the salt because it's like on the מנחה and
you bring it with it. Nevertheless we learn out for a פסוק
pasuk that no the salt is provided by the ציבור. tzibur Whatever
say Gavriely, she actually mentioned it yesterday. Yeah
I said that yesterday. Okay so the גמרא Gemara now goes on
like this. אמר ליה רב מרדכי Amar lei Rav Mordechai so now
why was the purpose of saying all of this? To say why
obviously we said that the בית דין Beis Din stipulated that the
כהנים Kohanim can use the salt and we said that they can
use the salt for their personal קרבן. korban, Now what we said
that means is when they're eating the קרבן. korban, And the גמרא
Gemara says well that makes sense, you wouldn't need a stipulation to
tell them that they could use the salt to burn their קרבן
korban? because to burn you know to burn the stuff that's burnt
because the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash provides the salt for everybody. So
how could I have even ever thought that it meant that we
needed to stipulate to allow them to use the salt for that?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara. is now going to answer. But
they thought they couldn't use the salt for their own personals? I
mean for their own שירים? shirayim? I'm a little confused at what
the גמרא Gemara hung up on. We said when there was a
statement that you can use the salt for the כהן's Kohen קרבן
korban, that it was stipulation of בית דין, din it meant for
their eating of their קרבן. korban And the גמרא Gemara is saying
well of course that's obvious that's what it means because there would
be no need for בית דין din to stipulate that they could
use their salt for the part of their קרבן korban, they're burning
because why would you need בית דין to stipulate? The בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, provides salt for everyone to burn their קרבן. korban So
that's the question: what was the הוה אמינא? hava amina? So
אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Mordechai leRav Ashi,
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, Rav Sheshet brei
deRav Idi, here is what רב ששת בריה דרב אידי Rav Sheshet
brei deRav Idi says: לא נצרכא אלא לבן בוכרי, lo nitzrecha ela
leBen Buchri, it's only needed according to the position of בן בוכרי.
Ben Buchri. Who is בן בוכרי? Ben Buchri? All right Jed is
at... I don't know what to say... he's fading in and out
again. Okay אלא
לבן בוכרי. ela leBen Buchri. דתנן detnan because we caught in the
משנה: Mishnah: אמר רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yehuda so רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says העיד בן בוכרי ביבנה, he'id Ben Buchri beYavne, בן בוכרי
Ben Buchri testified in יבנה, Yavne, כל כהן ששוקל אינו חוטא. kol
Kohen sheshokel eino chotei.
Any כהן Kohen that gives the שקל shekel will not sin, meaning
the כהנים Kohanim. were not required to give the שקלים, shekalim, they
were exempt, but if you wanted to it's not a problem. So
אמר לו רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Amar lo Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai,
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai said לא כי, lo
ki, that's not הלכה, halacha, אלא כל כהן שאינו שוקל חוטא. ela
kol Kohen she'eino shokel chotei. If you don't give your שקל shekel
you sin, you have to give a
שקל. shekel. אלא שהכהנים דורשים מקרא זה לעצמן, ela shehaKohanim dorshim mikra
ze le'atzman, the כהנים Kohanim, interpret the following פסוק pasuk to their
own advantage. What פסוק pasuk do they interpret to their own advantage?
The פסוק pasuk וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל. vechol minchat
Kohen kalil tihiyeh lo techachel. Every מנחה of a כהן kohen. shall
be totally burnt, it shall not be eaten. הואיל ואומר ho'il ve'omer
and say the לחם, lechem, לחם הפנים lechem hapanim שלנו הוא, shelanu
hu, since
if we were to give contribute to the ציבור tzibur. to the
communal funds then any of the מנחות menachot that would be brought,
even מנחות menachot would be partly owned by כהנים. Kohanim, So the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem would be partly owned by כהנים, Kohanim the
עומר omer would be partly owned by כהנים, Kohanim the לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim would be if we were to give to communal funds.
If it's partly owned by כהנים Kohanim what would have to be
done to it? It would have to be burnt. Now we don't
burn the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. All right this is their דרשה.
drasha. This is how their self-interest influences how they דרש darsh a
פסוק. pasuk. Okay? So הואיל ומשתי הלחם ולחם הפנים שלנו היא, ho'il
umishtei halechem ulechem hapanim shelanu hi, it would become ours because we
would be giving to communal funds, היך נאכלים, hech ne'echalim, how could
it be eaten? So from here we see that the כהנים Kohanim
says the כהנים Kohanim. that we do not have to contribute to
communal funds, not only we don't have to, we're not supposed to
contribute to communal funds. So there would be this debate about whether
the כהנים Kohanim would actually give the שקל. shekel. This is actually
very interesting to translate this into contemporary realities, I will do that
in a minute. Let's finish the point of the גמרא. Gemara So
the גמרא Gemara says ולבן בוכרי uleBen Buchri and so therefore according
to בן בוכרי Ben Buchri I would have thought that since they
don't contribute to communal funds therefore they're not allowed to use the
salt. The salt could only be used by ציבור tzibur. that contributed
to the communal funds for the buying of the salt. So there
had to be maybe a special stipulation to allow them to use
the salt. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ולבן בוכרי כיון
דלא קא מיחייב לאתויי כי
מייתי נמי חוטא הוא דקא מעייל חולין לעזרה. uleBen Buchri keivan dela
ka michayeiv le'atuyei ki mayiti nami chotei hu deka me'ayil chulin la'azarah.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, let me understand בן בוכרי.
Ben Buchri. He says if a כהן Kohen wants to give it's
not a problem, but if they're not obligated to give communal funds
then when they are giving, when they choose to give optionally, then
those monies never really are fully dedicated to the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. Now that's not exactly the same whether you're obligated or doing
by your own free will doesn't indicate that when you actually give
it whether you're fully giving it over or not. But the גמרא
Gemara thinks that if they're not obligated and they're giving it, then
those monies are not actually fully הקדש hekdesh and therefore things bought
by them are not fully קדוש. kadosh. So maybe they're privately owned
by the כהנים. kohanim So how could they opt to give if
they're not obligated to give? So the גמרא Gemara gives an easy
answer to this: דמייתי ומסר להו לציבור. demayiti umasar lehu latzibur. No,
when they give they actually fully give it over to the ציבור.
tzibur, So we have this fascinating debate: בן בוכרי Ben Buchri says
כהנים kohanim are not obligated to give to the communal funds, to
the שקלים, shekalim, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai says
they are obligated.
and but
according to בן בוכרי Ben Buchri if they do give optionally then
it does is owned by the ציבור. So according to him, anything
that's purchased by communal funds is not really part, the כהנים kohanim
don't have a portion in it. So how would the כהנים kohanim
be able to use the communal salt for their קרבנות? korbanos So
according to that maybe is why I needed the special stipulation that
you don't need a normal person to stipulate because that's what the
מחצית השקל mahatzit hashekel is for, but for the כהנים kohanim you
do. So the גמרא Gemara says סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina,
I would have thought
כי זכו להו רחמנא, ki zachu lehu rachmana, when did the תורה
Torah give them right, give you know give somebody right to the
salt? בישראל דאית להו לשכה, BeYisrael de-it lehu lishkah, to the normal
non-כהנים kohanim that they have contributed to the לשכה, lishkah, to the
communal funds. Top of כ"ט ע"א. chaf-tet amud aleph. הכהנים דלית להו
לשכה, Hakohanim de-leit lehu lishkah, the כהנים kohanim that do not have
a communal fund, לא זכו להו רחמנא, lo zachu lehu rachmana, maybe
they do not have the right to the salt. קא משמע לן
kamashma lan and therefore maybe it would help me that that's why
you had to be a special stipulation. So in the end we
do say that no, of course the כהנים kohanim can use the
salt for putting their קרבן korban on the fire. The חידוש chidush
is that בית דין even let them use their salt for their
eating of their קרבן. korban, Okay, but we do say that normally
the salt comes from communal funds and normally of course the כהנים
kohanim would have rights to that and the special stipulation was to
let them eat their קרבן, korban. but if the כהנים kohanim did
not contribute to communal funds, like according to בן בוכרי, Ben Buchri,
then you might have needed a special stipulation to allow them to
eat from the salt. Now this is quite fascinating, this whole approach
about whether they would contribute or not. First of all is the
question when it says הי הי בן בוכרי. Hei Hei Ben Buchri.
I know Rifka you're always interested in the question about whether they
actually had direct evidence of this. So take a look at, take
a look at this little תוספות, Tosafot שהכהנים דרשו מקרא זה לעצמן.
shehakohanim darshu mikra zeh le-atzman.
He said משמע דרבי יוחנן בן זכאי לא היה כהן. mashma de-Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai lo hayah kohen. Since כהנים kohanim דרשו darshun it
for their own interest,
it sounds like he's not a כהן. Kohen. והא דתנן בספרי, ve-hada
detnan be-Sifrei,
so when this is quoted over in ספרי Sifrei גבי פרה gabbei
parah by the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, שאמר רבי יוחנן בן זכאי
לתלמידיו מה שעשו ושרתו ידי שכחתי, she-amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai le-talmidav
mah she-asu ve-shartu yadai shachachti, what my hands did and served I
have forgotten. Meaning the amazing ספרי Sifrei that רבי יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai is saying, I don't remember
how the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah was brought, what I myself served
and hands performed I've forgotten exactly the rituals, right? לא דהוא עצמו
קאמר אלא כלומר על פי הוראתו. lav de-hu atzmo kama ela klomar
al pi hora'ato. It doesn't mean he personally did it, but it
means that it was done through his rulings and teachings and he
forgot how it was done. But I saw, I wanted first of
all you to see this it says sure we have רבי יוחנן
בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai quote that's also brings of the
ספרי Sifrei that he says like, I very, I forgot what I
myself did in the bringing of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So
ברייתא, braita. right, and he was right there. So תוספות Tosafot says
does that mean he did it or that he supervised it? But
anyway. And the בן בוכרי Ben Buchri also when it says הי
הי בן בוכרי, Hei Hei Ben Buchri, it sounds like he's actually
testifying to what was done. That's one point. The other point תוספות
Tosafos is quite fascinating besides the sort of idea of דרשה לעצמן
darsha le-atzman and the mention about the way in which, you know,
personal biases can affect how we interpret פסוקים pesukim of course, and
maybe it's a critique of כהנים kohanim, because כהנים kohanim, are not
seen as like the rabbinic class, so maybe there's sort of, maybe
there's like a critique there, like if you're not an official part
of the rabbinic class you're more likely to interpret things through your
own lens, not exactly clear. But beyond that is the interesting sort
of psychology of hey, I'm working for the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
I should not have to pay, you know, and like the question
of like the, you know, rabbis in a שול, shul, like hey,
you know, the שול shul pays my salary, I shouldn't have to
pay membership dues or the שול shul pays my salary, I shouldn't
have to donate to the, you know, to the to the annual
appeal.
And, you know, so there's a certain logic to that, but on
the other hand, then that means that you're not appreciating that you're
also served by this institution, even though you're hired and you work
for it, you're also being sort of served by this institution. And
what does it mean by the כהנים, kohanim? you know, to saying
in a way it's very nice that, you know, רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, who in a way is sort of
that transition after the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. and into sort of
more of a, you know, תורה-centered Torah reality, you know, he's more,
he's more critical of that whole approach, like, like
where the כהנים, kohanim? we don't have to give, you know, we
don't have to give to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. we are,
you know, in charge and we're the providers and so on. It
puts you, it positions you very differently when you say yes, I'm
doing the service but I'm also served by this and I have
to give as well. So anyway, I think that that's sort of
fascinating. It's also fascinating to say what does that mean? Does that
mean that all according
to this all the קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur were not brought for
the sake of the כהנים? kohanim They were brought for the sake
of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael excluding the כהנים? Kohanim. Or is it
that
somehow saying like no, you know, almost by definition, of course everything
is for, you know, the כהנים Kohanim, of course get credit for
it, you know, but, you know, and again that sort of speaks
to a certain sense of entitlement which is very much what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is speaking against, you know, even if even if
it's just a lousy, you know. half a shekel a year, whatever
it is, it does something to the whole dynamics of entitlement and
who's in charge and who's giving and who's getting. So it's רע
ra for the כהנים. Kohanim, Yeah. And the כהנים, Kohanim
and the salt isn't provided, so the כהנים, Kohanim how can they
enjoy the benefits of what's brought? In a sense? Well, it should
be there for them. Well, yeah, but that's the point. Can it
be there for them if they haven't actually contributed to it? You
know, and if it is, right, if they say, well, of course
the קרבנות korbanos, are for us, heck, we work here, you know,
so to create the whole dynamic of entitlement, like something to be
done for them even though they haven't contributed for it, they're just
entitled because they're part of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So I
think that's exactly what רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan is saying by saying,
you know, you've got to give.
So alright, let's now take, let's now move on.
I don't know why Ged is not able to hear this, but
anyway we have to continue.
So,
הגמרא HaGemara says like this. Where are we?
Okay, כמאן דאמר, Keman De-amar, the eighth, three lines from the top
of כה עמוד א, Kaf Hey Amud Aleph, העצים דפשיטא ליה לתנא
דמשל ציבור מנלן? He'etzim depishita lei letana demishel tzibur menalan? The wood,
that it's obvious to the תנא Tanna that that comes from the
ציבור, right? Because that was the example. Of course the wood is
provided by communal funds. How do we know that? דתניא, we turn
in the ברייתא. יכול יאמר הרי עלי עולה יביא עצים מתוך ביתו,
Yachol yomar harei alai ola yavi etzim mitoch beito, כדרך שמביא נסכים
מתוך ביתו. kederech shemeivi nesachim mitoch beito.
Maybe somebody who says I'll bring an עולה ola has to also
bring the wood from his house the same way he brings the
נסכים, nesachim, like again before we by the מנחה we talked about
the לבונה, here we're talking about the נסכים, nesachim, because I only
wanted to bring the animal, but you, the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash
your rules are obligating me to bring the נסכים, nesachim, to bring
the wine and the flour and the water. So maybe your rules
will also obligate me to bring the wood? Now again, there's a
big difference. The נסכים nesachim are a type of a קרבן, korban,
they accompany and they are offered. The wood is not offered, the
wood is more operating expenses. But maybe nevertheless I still have to
bring it. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, על העצים אשר על האש אשר
על המזבח, al ha'etzim asher al ha'eish asher al hamizbeach, that the
כהן kohen should arrange the עולה ola on the wood that's on
the fire that's on the מזבח. mizbeach, מה מזבח משל ציבור, ma
mizbeach mishel tzibur, of course the same way the altar is provided
by the community, right? It's the part of the institution of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, אף עצים ואש משל ציבור. af etzim ve'eish
mishel tzibur. So even the fire and the wood are something that
the community funds provide for, and you don't have to privately provide
for it. דברי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Divrei Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon,
that's רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon says. רבי אלעזר
בן שמוע אומר, Rabbi Elazar Ben Shamua omer, מה מזבח שלא נשתמש
בו הדיוט, ma mizbeach shelo nishtamesh bo hedyot, the same way an
altar was not used by a layperson. אף עצים ואש שלא נשתמש
בהן הדיוט. af etzim ve'eish shelo nishtamesh bahen hedyot.
So you have to get wood and fire that were used... not
used by a layperson, fresh wood and fire, not something that a
layperson has used and is donated. Fire? Well, you know, it basically
means, you know, it's like they didn't have matches, so it was
a little bit of a more of an effort to make fire.
So I mean it's obviously burning on wood, but still there's somebody
who's providing the fire. Meaning I can light you from my fire
and not have to give you my wood, right? So who has
to...
the fire has to come from a non-הדיוט hedyot source also. Right.
So meaning if I had fire in my backyard and I barbecued
on it, I can't take a log from it and go use
it to light the fire of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash I
have to make a new fire for the בית המקדש. The difference
between זר zar and הדיוט. hedyot.
Nothing actually. The difference here is that זר zar normally refers to
the sense of violating because it's an עבודה avoda that needs to
be done by a כהן.
So there's almost never neutral, meaning זר zar is almost always the
sense of foreigner, outsider who's going into a space that he doesn't
belong. Here it's a question of like where is it provided from?
Is it provided from הקדש hekdesh funds or from non-הקדש hekdesh funds?
So it's not that sense of a person serving where he shouldn't
be serving.
זר zar is almost like alien, foreigner, it has that sort of
outsider resonance.
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, there you go. So okay, אף עצים ואש
שלא נשתמש בהן הדיוט. af etzim ve'eish shelo nishtamesh bahen hedyot. הגמרא
HaGemara says, מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu? What's the difference? איכא בינייהו חדתא,
ika beinayhu chadta, new wood. Meaning, the one that says it has
to be provided by הקדש hekdesh and not by a הדיוט hedyot
does not say that it has to be new wood. He could
say the בית המקדש could go and use their funds and buy
some wood that was used by somebody else for some other purpose,
but now it's owned by the מקדש Mikdash and the מקדש Mikdash
provides it. So one is really a question of who has purchased
it and who is providing it. The other is a question of
is it new or is it used? And you could also have
the flip. You could have something that's brand new and is provided
by a הדיוט, hedyot, right? I'll take my freshly cut wood to
the מקדש. Mikdash. So they're really saying something very different. One is
saying it's provided by the מקדש, Mikdash, and the other is saying
that it has to be fresh. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, עתיקי, atiki, and old wood, לא, you can't use? והכתיב, ve-haktiv,
does not the verse say... When David sort of dedicated the space
of the בית המקדש, ויאמר ארונה אל דוד יקח ויעל אדוני המלך
הטוב בעיניו: Vayomer Arona el David yikach veya'al adoni hamelech hatov be'einav:
Take and offer up, you know, these cattle what's good in your
eyes, see the בקר bakar for עולה, olah, you can use the
cows for an עולה, olah, המורגים hamorigim וכלי הבקר לעצים, veklei habakar
le'etzim,
and the threshing implements, threshing implements, what's it called when you crush
the grain? Threshing. No, no, but what's the process called when you
crush the grain? Not that's not threshing, that's grinding. Grinding? Winnowing. Grinding?
No, that's when you're making the flour. I'm talking about when you
when the flour in the field, when threshing, that is threshing, threshing
is when you throw it up and the wind separates it. That's
winnowing.
Okay, okay, so the
המורגין, hamorgin, so the threshing implements, כלי הבקר לעצים, klei habakar le'etzim,
and the implements of the cattle you can use for wood. So
you see we're using, you know, used wood for fire wood for
מזבח. mizbeach. So the גמרא Gemara. says הכא נמי בחדתין, hacha nami
bechadatin,
no,
no, it was brand new vessels that have yet to be used.
So it's interesting even though they've been cut and fashioned and made
into vessels, since they have not yet been used, they're considered new.
Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara says, yes, that you still
say you need to use new wood and that since it has
yet to actually have been used, even though it was made into
a vessel, it's new. מאי מוריגין, Mai morigin, what does מוריגין morigin
mean? אמר עולא: Amar Ulla: מיטה של טרבל. mita shel tarbal.
Okay, a bed of טרבל, tarbal, which is like spikes. מאי מיטה
של טרבל, Mai mita shel tarbal, so the גמרא Gemara says, very
good, what does that mean? So אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda:
עיזא דקורקשא. iza dekorkasa. Well, again, that helps, but somehow that also
means, רש"י Rashi says, a קורקשא korkasa is a thick plank, and
somehow עיזא iza means like, again, like a spiked plank. So they
would have the cattle draw a plank that has all of these
spikes coming out of it, sort of like cleats, you know, with
metal spikes, and it would crush,
no, that's thresh, and it would crush the, it would crush the,
you know the chaff, not the chaff, whatever it's called, the thing
that holds the kernel.
So and
it's to separate greater seeds from a plant. There you go. All
right. דדשו בה דשתא Dedashu bei dishta that you use for threshing.
אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: מאי קרא, mai kra, where do
you see this from a פסוק? pasuk? הנה שמתיך למורג חרוץ חדש:
Hinei sammicha lemorag charutz chadash: Behold I have created you like this
מורג morag with fresh, you know, spikes, בעל פיפיות ba'al pipiyot of
many, you know, of many again like mouths, but really like of
many teeth, תדוש הרים tadush harim and you shall thresh mountains. So
you see a מורג morag is something used to thresh. Okay, wonderful.
What have we learned from this? We've learned that the salting was
done with communally provided salt for ישראל, it was done at the
for the מנחה at the ראש המזבח, rosh hamizbe'ach, for the meat
at the middle of the at the, you know, on the ramp,
anything that you would burn you would salt ahead of time, and
that we learned that the wood and the salt were provided by
communal funds. That interesting discussion about whether the כהנים Kohanim would contribute
to the communal funds, and that the כהנים Kohanim, were allowed to
use the salt for salting the meat that they would actually, that
they would actually eat. Okay, now we go on to the next
משנה. Mishna. Funds or just a half שקל shekel or is it
also נדבות nedavot that the people, primarily it's the מחצית השקל, machatzis
hashekel, yeah. I mean the נדבות nedavot were more used for things
like the עולה olah for קיץ המזבח kayitz hamizbe'ach for like, you
know, special sacrifice.
How did they do all their expenses with a half שקל shekel
from everyone? I don't know, don't know how many people contributed and
how many their expenses were, but it's a good question. All right,
I hear your point, like, didn't the בית המקדש have an annual
appeal to make up the deficit in the budget from the membership
dues?
Right, more collect-o-matic. Yeah, I hear the point. All right, so let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishna. נתערב, Nitarv, now we go
on to, we move from the actual, as you see, like מנחות
Menachos is this quick digest of all the things that we did
in זבחים. Zevachim. So let's see what we've discussed by now. We
discussed שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, we've of course discussed our friend פיגול,
pigul, we discussed when non-כשר כהנים kosher Kohanim do the עבודה, avodah,
and which things require כהנים Kohanim, or not כהנים, Kohanim, and that
was how we got into this whole thing about the salt and
what not which of the עבודות avodos require כהנים, and now we
are discussing what happens when things get mixed up. You might remember
that from זבחים Zevachim when blood gets mixed up with blood and
animals with animals, so now we're discussing that as well. Okay, נתערב,
nitarv, let's take a look at the משנה: Mishna: נתערב קומץ בקומץ
חברו, nitarv kometz bekometz chaveiro, במנחת כהנים, beminchas Kohanim, במנחת כהן משיח.
beminchas Kohen Mashiach.
So you have your קומץ kometz and you accidentally dropped it and
it got mixed up into what, קומץ
חברך, kometz chaverka, another, another קומץ kometz of another מנחה. We're two
כהנים, we each took our קומץ, kometz, we have our כלי, kli,
we bump into each other, you know those little ads for Reese's
Peanut Butter Cups? You got, you got your peanut butter in my
chocolate! So you got your קומץ kometz in my קומץ, kometz, so
we bump into each other, it gets mixed up. Okay, what's? Can
we just bring both of them on the מזבח? mizbeach. They both
have to go to the מזבח, mizbeach we'll burn it all, maybe
just bring both of them on the מזבח. mizbeach. What? How would
you have it in your hand? Well let's look at the... but
no, but after you've taken it in the hand you put it
in a כלי. kli.
No you don't go straight from the hand? You do later, but
this is before you do that. Yeah, you take it from the
hand and you put it into a כלי. kli. And then you
pour it from the כלי kli or you... okay. I think you
just... I think you just like... I'm not sure actually. I have
to find out. What's the purpose of the כלי? kli? Well the
purpose of the כלי kli is to sanctify, to you know is
that that's like an act of הקדשה hakdashah like collecting the blood
in the כוס. kos. Let me see how the רמב"ם Rambam says
how it was put exactly on the
מזבח. mizbeach. Wait there was a מחלוקת machloket because you know we
had that... no, the מחלוקת machloket was whether you put the לבונה
in the same כלי kli or not. No but whether you like
turn it over, right? Like I say in the first book you
take everything and then you turn it over and it kind of
like you you actually tip it again. No no no our debate
was whether it was דף פ"ט. Daf Pei Tet. This is basing
itself on the רמב"ם Rambam but the פשט peshat of all the
גמרות gemaras is that the לבונה was in a separate כלי. kli.
How you would get it from the כלי kli to the מזבח
mizbeach let me take a look.
נותנו בכלי שרת ומקדשו בכלי שרת. notno bikli sharet ve-mekaddsho bikli sharet.
Yeah the רמב"ם Rambam says, the רמב"ם Rambam at least says ונותנו
על גבי האש מכלי שרת. ve-noteno al gabi ha-ish mi-kli sharet. So
you take basically take it straight from the כלי. kli. No you
don't take it, you basically turn the, you know you basically turn
the כלי kli upside down and it looks like you had it
in a bowl and you oil it. Wait you grab it once
and then you put it in the... right. And then you don't
handle it directly. Michael got his picture. Okay, so alright, so our
two קומצים kommetzim got mixed up, okay, or it got mixed up
with מנחת כהן minchat kohen or מנחת כהן משיח minchat kohen mashiach
with other things that are burnt. Michael is bringing the מנחה of
a כהן or of the כהן גדול kohen gadol which is fully
burnt, okay. So now my קומץ kommetz got mixed up. So okay
the solution is obvious: burn everything. You have to burn each קומץ,
kommetz, you have to burn the קומץ kommetz and the מנחת הכהנים,
minchat ha-kohanim, so you burn everything and you've done what you're supposed
to do with these things. So the הלכה halacha is fine. Or
במנחת נסכים, bi-minchat nesachim, how about a מנחה that came with the
wine that comes with a קרבן? korban That also is fully burnt.
So in all those cases שפירא איתכשר, shapira itkasher, just burn everything.
Very nice and easy. What is going to happen if it gets
mixed up with something that isn't supposed to be burnt? That will
be the next משנה. mishna. But this משנה mishna is: this קומץ
kommetz got mixed up with other things, other types of מנחות minchas
that are fully burnt or a קומץ kommetz that's fully burnt, just
burn it all and you're fine. Now we have רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda though. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer, במנחת כהן משיח ובמנחת
נסכים פסולה. bi-minchat kohen mashiach u-vi-minchat nesachim pesulah. If it gets mixed
up with the מנחה of a כהן גדול kohen gadol or the
מנחה of the נסכים nesachim that comes with the wine that comes
with the קרבן, korban it's פסול. pasul. Why? שזו בלילתה עבה וזו
בלילתה רכה והן בולעות זו מזו. she-zo bililatah avah ve-zo bililatah rakkah
ve-hen bole'ot zo mi-zo. This one is a thick mixture and the
other one is a thin mixture and they absorb from one another.
What does that mean? It means that the normal מנחה is an
עישרון issaron of flour, which we said is basically two and a
half liters of flour, mixed up with a לוג log of שמן.
shemen. And a לוג log of שמן shemen is about half a
liter, a one to five ratio. The מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, if
you might remember from the מוסף, musaf, whenever we say מוסף musaf
we say what do you bring with it? ועישרון שמן, v'isaron shemen,
right? You bring with what even with the lamb and the smallest
animal you bring a רביעית revi'it of a הין hin of oil.
Now a הין hin is twelve לוגים, logs, so a quarter of
twelve is three. So for the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim you have
the same amount of flour, the two and a half liters, but
you actually have a liter and a half of oil, three times
as much oil, so it's a much looser mixture. And the same
is true by the מנחה of the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So
now you have a very loose mixture, right imagine it's almost like
batter and one is more like dough. Okay, so you basically have
these two get mixed up. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you
can't just burn it all because basically you've redefined what you have
here. You no longer have a dough קומץ kommetz and a batter
מנחת נסכים. minchat nesachim. You now have,
if they just touch at one point, the proportions change. So your
dough is not the right proportions and your batter is not the
right... whatever they touched to the other. Well
then you're not burning the whole קומץ kommetz and you're not burning
the whole מנחה. No you can't... well you
can't be מקריב makriv less than
a קומץ. kommetz. The קומץ kommetz you have to be מקריב makriv
the whole thing. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it is invalid
because you have changed the physical reality of what you have. Alright,
so let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara
תנן התם, tenan hatam, we taught over there, and he makes direct
reference to the משנה mishna in זבחים. Zevachim. דם שנתערב במים, dam
she-nitarev be-mayim,
so water gets mixed up with, blood gets mixed up with water.
So the blood of a קרבן korban. gets falls into some water.
אם יש בו מראית דם כשר. im yesh bo marit dam kasher.
If it still looks like blood, it's כשר. kasher. Now then
because interestingly and I've mentioned this before, when you deal with mixtures
by food, by כשרות, kashrus, the question is does it still have
the taste of the non-kosher food?
What's pork
doing in your קישקע kishka anyway? Here, I like giving the pork
example because it gets everybody very nervous. Like, pork! Anyway, so but
when you're not dealing with food, taste is not the most dominant
characteristic. Most dominant characteristic for most of us is what things look
like, right? Isn't it מראית עין? maris ayin? You think for a
מקוה, mikva, no? Yes. So for things like מקוה mikva and קרבנות
korbanos etc., how it appears really defines much more whether it's considered
nullified or not nullified. So it says, if it still appears like
blood, as blood is still present, and you can do the ביזורת
הדם. bizoras hadam. But interestingly, what does it mean that it still
appears like blood? Like if I have the example again about כשרות,
kashrus, it wouldn't have to have a dominant pork taste to be
טרף. traif. It would have to have a טרף traife pork taste,
would be enough to be טרף. traif. What about here if it
has a little bloody look but it doesn't look like blood itself?
One minute, so if you look at תוספות Tosafos in ויש בו
מראית דם כשר, veyesh bo mar'is dam kasher,
this תוספות Tosafos is about eight lines from the bottom. He says,
לא באדמומית מעט מכשיר, lo beadmumis meat machshir,
not with a little reddishness is it considered כשר. kasher. אלא מראית
דם גמור קאמר. ela mar'is dam gamur kaamar. It has to really
look like blood. Not it looks like it's a little bloody, it
looks like blood, okay? למיעוטי היכא דדיהא מראיתו, limiutei heicha dedeiha mar'iso,
as opposed to a case where it actually looks paler than blood.
And then he proves it from the later גמרא Gemara, that actually
it has to look like blood itself. So this is quite interesting.
And it makes a certain amount of sense. If you want to
invalidate something, a tiny trace amount of pork taste makes it invalid.
Like you don't want trace amounts of poison in your food, or
trace amounts of, you know, of a carcinogen or whatever. For something
bad, even a trace amount that's detectable makes it not good. But
if you want it to be good, if you want it to
count as blood, then it's not enough that it look like there's
a little blood there, that it really has to look like blood
to count as blood. So it's very interesting, the asymmetry between how
we determine a ביטול bitul question here as opposed to a ביטול
bitul question by כשרות. kashrus. You had a question? Isn't it also...
you said about visual, but there's also sense of smell. Like blood
has a certain smell, very strong, so does like water. Right, but
normally that's not, again, that's not the dominant thing. For most of
us, yes those things do matter how we identify, but our primary
way of identifying things is visual. Now there is a גמרא Gemara
that talks about whether smell matters and whether ריחא מילתא reicha milsa
or not, but that's not the primary thing. What about the עזרה?
Azara? They were open, right? Open air, the rain could have gotten
into... Interesting question. Maybe that's why you needed this הלכה. halacha. A
little rain, it still looks like blood, right? That's a good point.
Well there's
water for washing their hands and for washing things as well, you
definitely talked about water before. Was this one of the עשרה נסים
asara nissim that they say? No, לא
קבוע. lo kavo. Great anyway, alright, so if it still looks like
blood, it's כשר. kasher. נתערב ביין, nisarev beyayin, if it gets mixed
up in wine,
רואין אותו כאילו הוא מים. ro'in oso ke'ilu hu mayim. We look
at the wine as if it were water, and we'll say if
it were water and it would still look like blood, it's כשר.
kasher. Now that's actually fascinating because תוספות Tosafos points out, you know,
that's a לקולא. lekula. Why don't we just say it's all red
and red, you can't detect it, it looks like blood,
so it should be פסול posul because it doesn't look like blood?
No, we're prepared to sort of imagine the wine as a less
dominant presence in order to say that it could in theory still
look like blood in this mixture and therefore it's
כשר. kasher. תוספות Tosafot says, you know, he doesn't know where we
get that from. Normally that's not a normal principle about ביטול. bitul.
This נירי נירי niri niri sometimes we say to be מחמיר machmir
but here we're being מקיל, maikil, we're allowing it to count as
good wine.
Okay. נתערב בדם בהמה או בדם חיה, nisarev bedam behema o bedam
chaya, if blood gets mixed up with blood of a
non-קרבן, korban okay? One minute. רואין אותו כאילו הוא מים. ro'in oso
ke'ilu hu mayim. Again, you look at the other blood as if
it's water, and if this thing would... the original blood would still
be visible, then it is going to be כשר, kasher, if not,
not. Okay, you want to add something James? We're assuming it's still
good blood, not good wine. Still good blood and you can use
it on the
מזבח. mizbeach Okay? It's much more... no, because if we looked at
it, if we didn't pretend the wine was water, we would say
this thing doesn't look like blood anymore, it looks like wine.
But if it's water, then the water has less of an impact
on it.
You're going to have to question it all at some point? Yes.
Now, רבי יהודה אומר אין דם מבטל דם. Rabbi Yehuda omer ein
dam mevatel dam. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, if blood
gets mixed up with blood, then even if there's a lot of
non-קרבן korban blood, it does not create ביטול. bitul. And therefore you're
never going to have a problem. No matter how much non-קרבן korban
blood gets mixed up, no ביטול bitul occurs when it's like and
like, and therefore you can always be זורק את הדם. zoreik es
hadam. So
הגמרא... hagimara... אמר רבי יוחנן... amar Rabbi Yochanan... says Rabbi Yochanan... And
ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. v’shnehem mikra echad darshu. They both got this
from one פסוק, pasuk, this idea about whether דם dam is מבטל
mivatel דם dam or not. What's the
פסוק? pasuk? ולקח מדם הפר ומדם השעיר. v’lakach midam hapar u-midam haseir.
This is by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur where we assume it means that he mixed the two bloods
together of the cow and of the goat and then he put
it on the קרנות karnot of the מזבח. mizbeach. So he mixed
the two together but it's still considered דם הפר ודם השעיר, dam
hapar v’dam haseir, still considered you have both bloods even though, as
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, there's obviously a lot more
blood from an ox than from a goat.
הדבר ידוע, hadavar yadua, it's known, שדמו של פר מרובה מדמו של
שעיר, she-damo shel par merubah mi-damo shel sair, that the ox's blood
is a lot more than the goat blood. Why does the גמרא,
Gemara why does the תורה even after they're mixed together consider it
both bloods are still present? So רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri, the Rabbis
hold now the top of the עמוד, doing all of עמוד, aren't
we? Thought we weren't going to get through today, look at that,
מכאן לעולים שאין מבטלין זה את זה. mikan l’olin she’ein mevatlin zeh
et zeh. From here we learn a principle that things that go
on the מזבח mizbeach do not are not מבטל mevatel one another.
So if you have blood of a non-קרבן, korban. that will be
מבטל mivatel blood of a קרבן. korban But if you have bloods
of different קרבנות, korbanos. they do not create ביטול. bitul. And that
key line which would have been so critical when we were learning
זבחים, Zevachim, I told you about it because you remember some of
those משניות mishnayos in זבחים Zevachim were a חטאת chatat gets mixed
up with other animals and this gets mixed up and this gets
mixed up, and the question was whatever happened to ביטול bitul as
the גמרא Gemara asks it once but forgot about it for a
lot of those discussions. And the real answer was based on this
principle that אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה. ein olin mevatlin zeh
et zeh. Things that are קרבנות korbanos. that go on the מזבח
do not effect ביטול bitul one on the other when they get
mixed up. If it's something that's a non-קרבן, korban, blood of another
animal that will effect ביטול. bitul. So that's the principle the Rabbis
learn out from the fact the תורה calls it the blood of
the goat and the blood of the ox. But רבי יהודה סבר,
Rebbe Yehuda savar, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, it's not about
their קרבן korban. status, מכאן למין במינו שאינו בטל. mikan l’min bemino
she’eino batel. Here you have like and like do not create ביטול.
bitul. So there's a big difference, meaning they overlap in the case
of the blood of the goat and the blood of the שעיר,
sair, but there's a huge difference between them. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
would say it doesn't have to be a קרבן korban discussion at
all. Let's say you get a טרף treif chicken and a
כשר kosher chicken and a little drop of טרף treif chicken soup
falls into your, whatever wouldn't be set properly, falls into your כשר
kosher chicken soup. It could be a tiny drop in a huge
vat and it's טרף treif because מין במינו לא בטל. min bemino
lo batel. It has nothing to do with קרבנות. korbanos And the
רבנן Rabbanan say no, no, it has everything to do with קרבנות.
korbanos, It doesn't have to be blood and blood, it could even
be different types of things that get mixed up, it's a special
דין that by קרבנות korbanos things do not create ביטול. bitul. So
there's a huge difference between their positions, which is why you normally
never hear of this because we rule like the רבנן. Rabbanan. So
the real relevance of this position is by קרבנות, korbanot. whereas according
to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda you would hear about this all the
time, this would fly every minute in your kitchen, מין במינו לא
בטל. min bemino lo batel. Right, רש"י Rashi actually rules like רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda but we don't rule like רש"י. Rashi. Okay, yes,
maybe distinction in terms of the קרבנות korbanot though between bloods that
are both used, end up at the same end destination and maybe
that's why it doesn't matter versus things that have different
purposes and therefore I'm going to get into this tension of well
that's basically anything that's עולים. olin. I don't think so. I think
עולים olin is regardless of whether there's other similarities or not but
I'd have to check. Okay, so they learn out very different things
from this
פסוק. pasuk. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to analyze it.
רבנן סברי מכאן לעולים שאין מבטלין זה את זה. Rabbanan savri mikan
l’olin she’ein mevatlin zeh et zeh. Why did you learn out one
thing rather than the other? This aspect of the blood of the
goat and the blood of the ox has both features. It's a
מין במינו, min bemino, like and like, and it's two things that
are offered on the מזבח. What makes you decide to emphasize one
feature over the other? What's the basis of the רבנן Rabbanan versus
רבי יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask. רבנן סברי מכאן לעולים שאין מבטלין זה את זה, Rabbanan
savri mikan l’olin she’ein mevatlin zeh et zeh, they learn out that
עולים olin do not negate one
another. ודילמא משום דמין במינו הוא? v’dilma mishum d’min bemino hu? Maybe
because it's like and like? And maybe
רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda? explanation is the right one? No. אי אשמעינן
מין במינו ולא אשמעינן עולים, ei ashmi’inan min bemino v’lo ashmi’inan olin,
if the תורה had given us an example of like and like
without it being עולים, olin, then
I would agree that that's what it's trying to teach me. השתא
דאשמעינן עולים, hashta d’ashmi’inan olin, since the תורה's example was within the
world of
עולים, olin, משום דעולים, mishum d’olin, so I will assume it's because
of the world of עולים. olin. So the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא
עד דאיכא מין במינו ועולים? v’dilma ad d’ika min bemino v’olin? Maybe
you need both features to prevent ביטול, bitul, that it be both
עולים olin and like and like, and only then is there no
ביטול? bitul? קשיא. kashya. All right, that's difficult. They're assuming it's only
one characteristic, which is why there's no ביטול bitul and not both.
And now it says the same to רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda רבי
יהודה סבר מכאן למין במינו שאינו בטל, Rebbe Yehuda savar mikan l’min
bemino she’eino batel, here it tells me מין במינו min bemino is
not בטל. batel. ודילמא משום דעולים הוא? v’dilma mishum d’olin hu? Maybe
the reason there's no ביטול bitul is because they're עולים? olin? No.
אי אשמעינן עולים במין שאינו מינו, ei ashmi’inan olin bemin she’eino mino,
had the תורה given us an example of עולים olin that were
different types, not blood and blood, but you know blood and I
don't know wine or
something, then I would have said yes, it's telling us that עולים
olin don't create ביטול. bitul. השתא דאשמעינן מין במינו. hashta d’ashmi’inan min
bemino. and the Torah giving us the example of like and like,
of blood and blood, משום דמין במין הוא, mishum demin bemin hu,
I'll say that that's the salient feature, the fact that it's blood
and not that it's a קרבן. korban. So גמרא Gemara says דיוקא
דאיכא מין במין diyuka de'ika min bemin ואיכא ve'ika maybe both features
important? קשיא. kashya. That's difficult. You know, this גמרא Gemara was basically
trying to get at like what's at their debate and it really
didn't wasn't able to to to deduce anything. So basically it says,
look, this has two features, you could reasonably say one feature determines
not the other, or you could say both features determine, what points
you to saying it's feature A rather than feature B or rather
than A and B? And the גמרא Gemara says, you know, we
don't know. That just the רבנן Rabbanan understand that will think that
what the what you know, the them and you and you could
explain it like this although in the end, you know, at a
certain point you know it's hard to go further. That you know,
there are ראשונים Rishonim that explained it as a logic to רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda. of מין במין לא בטיל, min bemin lo batil,
that ביטול bitul occurs when things are different, cause when you have
difference you can eradicate difference. So if I have like a little
pork taste falling into my chicken soup and now I can't taste
the pork, so I can say it's like stopped existing because it
had a distinct identity and it lost it, it stopped existing. If
I have a trace, a drop a drop of טרף treif chicken
soup that falls into my chicken soup, I can't say it's lost
its identity cause there was never a difference to be then you
know, eradicated and it's all chicken soup. So there's a certain logic
to saying מין במין לא בטיל. min bemin lo batil. On the
other hand, there's a certain logic to say it's a special דין
by קרבנות. korbanot We have tons of special laws by קרבנות korbanot
and in particular in the area of ביטול, bitul, there are גמרות
Gemarot you know, about this whole thing about יקדש כמוהו yikdash kamo
and whatever a lot of גמרות Gemarot about special laws about קרבנות
korbanot. and particularly in relating to ביטול. bitul. So you could understand
that you could look at this and say it's because of the
קרבן distinction. So at the end of the day it still doesn't
explain why the רבנן Rabbanan were inclined to think like oh this
is a קרבן exception and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was inclined by
the logic of מין במין min bemin and that's sort of what
the גמרא Gemara says at the end of the day, we don't
know in the end what really informed one position over the other.
So wait, so apply this to a מנחה because רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda was about to apply it to a מנחה. So let's look
at what the גמרא Gemara does. So now what is this huge
תוספות Tosafot. that made today's דף very easy? It's actually not a
very conceptually interesting תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot tries to go through all
of שס Shas and see, is it really true that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda holds מין... well first of all he asks one question
which is that there's an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that you
don't mix the blood of the goat and the blood of the
ox. You only mix them when you get to the top of
the מזבח and not when you apply it on the corners. If
you didn't mix it ahead of time the whole פסוק pasuk drops
off, so where then do you get the principle of אין עולין
מבטלין זה את זה ein olin mevatlin ze et ze cause that
seems to be a generally accepted principle? That's one question he asks.
But for the most of it what he asks are cases where
it seems that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda admits that there is ביטול
bitul by מין במין min bemin and he tries to resolve it.
And one of the primary ways he resolves this, although he goes
back and forth whether he's happy with this, is a difference between
לח בלח lach belach and יבש ביבש. yavesh beyavesh. If it's two
liquids being mixed up, that's where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it
does not get nullified. But let's say it's two solids, which is
like some of the cases in the גמרא Gemara in זבחים, Zevachim,
like this קרבן and that קרבן. So I had my clear one
טרף treif chicken and a thousand kosher chickens. One chicken was not
שחט shachted properly. Okay, so that's מין במין. min bemin. Would I
say according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it's not all one homogeneous
mass? Each one is still distinct from the other. Maybe that would
be ביטול. bitul. And that has to do with maybe you know,
that ביטול bitul might operate differently when things are physically distinct than
when they're one big mass. When they're one big mass you could
say it loses independent identity, they all become one with everything else
and so on. Or you could say the opposite when רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says it doesn't stop being chicken soup because all you
have here is chicken soup. Okay, how יבש ביבש yavesh beyavesh operates
might be a little different. יבש ביבש yavesh beyavesh might operate by
the fact that I can pick this up and say I don't
know whether this is the kosher or טרף treif one, I'll just
assume that by the majority. So maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
admit to that case. It's not by the fact that it loses
its identity through everything being the same or it retains its identity
through everything being the same, it's that you pick each one up
individually and you say I wonder which one this is and you
decide based on the percentages. Okay, so that's anyway a lot of
what תוספות Tosafot is trying to figure out, that it doesn't seem
like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda always says לא בטיל. lo batil. And
that basically you're saying the answer is it depends if it's לח
בלח lach belach or יבש ביבש. yavesh beyavesh. That's the one answer
תוספות Tosafot is most happy with, but yeah, he has other... he
I mean it's a huge תוספות Tosafot and that's really the one
clear answer that emerges although he doesn't feel it always answers all
the questions. Yeah, did ביטול bitul vs עיקר וטפל ikar ve'tafel we
had before?
What? עיקר וטפל? ikar ve'tafel? Well, that's exactly what I was going
to... now we're going to after we've introduced this, now we're going
to see how this is relevant to our משנה. mishna. So let's
just read two more lines. Part of the קרבנות discussion versus the
כלל klal discussion being a discussion of ביטול's bitul effect in what
we had there? We only know ביטול bitul by איסור. issur. Now
we're dealing with something else. Oh yeah, that bit of... what about
היתר בהיתר? heter be'heter? But no, it doesn't seem that that's at
the heart of it. I mean, there is some discussion about that,
but that doesn't seem that that's at the heart of it. תנן.
Tnan. So let's take a look at how, now that we've introduced
this background, let's see how it applies to our משנה. mishna. תנן,
Tnan, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר, omer: דמנחת כהן משיח ומנחת נסכים
פסולה, de'minchat kohen mashiach u'minchat nesachim psula, if the קומץ komets gets
mixed up with these מנחות menachot that are higher degree of oil,
it's פסול. pasul. Why? זה בלילתו עבה וזה בלילתו רכה. ze blilato
ava v'ze blilato raka. One has a thick mixture and the other
a thin one, meaning one is like a dough and the other's
a batter, ובלעו זה מזה, u'balu ze mize, they absorb one from
the other. So the גמרא Gemara says וכי בלעו זה מזה מאי
הוי? v'chi balu ze mize mai havei? Who cares if they absorb
one from the other? מין במינו הוא, min b'mino hu, it's all
מין במינו min b'mino because you have oil and oil and flour
and flour. Now תוספות Tosafot, says, and I share this with תוספות,
Tosafot I was actually really struggling with this גמרא Gemara and hoping
תוספות Tosafot would answer it. תוספות Tosafot says he doesn't know what
the גמרא Gemara is talking about, because what does this have to
do with ביטול? bitul? What this has to do with is
changing the proportions. It stops being dough and it becomes batter-y and
stops being batter and it becomes doughy. It's not a question of
ביטול. bitul. The גמרא Gemara thinks that the reason for רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda this is a problem is because what will happen is
a little oil from let's say the batter קרבן goes into the
dough קרבן, and that oil becomes בטל. batel. And now it no
longer exists from the perspective of the batter קרבן. And vice versa,
like it's ביטול. bitul. So תוספות Tosafot says, well, why is it
בטל? batel? It's oil and oil! That shouldn't create ביטול. bitul. But
the fun thing is, who said anything about ביטול? bitul? Says, like,
the actual physical reality has changed. So anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara
question, that it thinks that the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda problem here
is ביטול. bitul. Says it's not ביטול, bitul, it's oil and oil.
Let's see what the answer is. Or blood? Before they were different
weight, different thickness? Well, they obviously different weight because one has more
oil. No but their blood? When their blood was short? That could
be too, or so? One's thicker, one's thinner, that's the key. No,
because it's not defined by blood by virtue of being thick or
thin. That's just the question of like where did it come from.
Here, you know, one קרבן you have distinct discussions in מנחות Menachot
because these are manufactured items. So the nature of this is a
batter and the nature of this is a, you
know, כדאמר רב פפא. k'de'amar Rav Papa. What? Oh no, אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Papa, that's about מחשבה, machshava, that's not about the
physical reality. So the גמרא Gemara says let's see the גמרא's Gemara
answer. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, קסבר kasavar רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, כל
שהוא מין במינו ודבר אחר. kol she'hu min b'mino v'davar acher.
If you have מין במינו, min b'mino, oil and oil are mixing
in here because that's what we're saying, like why should the oil
be בטל? batel? It's mixing with oil of the other קרבן. Ah,
but there's something else here, the flour. Okay, so you have oil
and oil and flour. סלק
את מינו כמי שאינו, salek et mino k'mi she'eino, ignore... so here
are my two קרבנות. This is my batter and this is my
dough. And here they like overlap right here, they're overlapping. And the
problem is we assume somehow the problem is that the oil that's
coming from here becomes בטל. batel. That's how we're defining the problem.
So we're saying it shouldn't be בטל batel because there's oil here
too, there's no ביטול. bitul. The גמרא says the presence of other
oil does not prevent ביטול, bitul, it just doesn't effect ביטול. bitul.
So it's true that there's oil here that won't create ביטול, bitul,
but something else will be מבטל mevatel the oil that got absorbed:
the flour. Okay, כל שהוא מין במינו ודבר אחר. kol she'hu min
b'mino v'davar acher. You have מין במינו, min b'mino, oil and oil
are mixing in here in this other one, but you have something
else, you have flour. סלק את מינו כמי שאינו, salek et mino
k'mi she'eino, ignore the oil, oil won't affect ביטול bitul but it
won't prevent ביטול. bitul. ושאינו מינו רבה עליו ומבטלו, v'she'eino mino raba
alav u'mevatlo, and the flour here is going to be מבטל mevatel
the oil. So it's a very strange question. For some reason the
גמרא understands that what bothers רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by the mixing
is ביטול, bitul, and since we thought רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda didn't
hold of ביטול, bitul, so the גמרא's answer is, ah, it's still
going to be בטל, batel, the flour will create ביטול. bitul. But
as תוספות says, who the heck needs ביטול bitul here? You've basically
changed, you no longer have dough and batter, you have a doughy
batter and a batter-y dough and that's the problem. Okay, so the
גמרא nevertheless answers it like that, which leaves the question and according
to the חכמים, Chachamim, why is it okay? Why don't the חכמים
Chachamim hold of ביטול? bitul? Right, now we don't understand why the
חכמים Chachamim feel it's good. If there's a real issue of ביטול
bitul going on, so the חכמים Chachamim who certainly hold of ביטול,
bitul, let them say that it's בטל. batel. All right, that if
the issue were batter, dough, whatever, maybe that's not an issue for
the חכמים. Chachamim. Ready to do chicken feed? For רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, if you're...